<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>dra4ov</title>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/"/>
 <updated>2021-12-25T20:43:55+01:00</updated>
 <id>http://localhost:4000</id>
 <author>
   <name></name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>moving to estonia</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/12/24/moving-to-estonia"/>
   <updated>2021-12-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2021/12/24/moving-to-estonia</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/moving-to-estonia/e-estonia.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;estonia&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have made the decision to move to Tallinn, Estonia. In this post I’m going to chart out my reasons for doing so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some background: I’m 27 years old, I studied Electrical Engineering at KU Leuven, currently living in Brussels (Belgium). After finishing my studies I have worked at Nokia and then 2 startups (as an employee). The experience of working at Nokia has taught me I’m not really cut out for a big corporate structure; whereas the experience at the startups has taught me how relatively underdeveloped this field is in Belgium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The decision to migrate always has two factors: push and pull. Push factors are the reasons why people decide to &lt;em&gt;leave&lt;/em&gt;, pull factors are the reasons that &lt;em&gt;attract&lt;/em&gt; people to a certain place. Let’s first look at the push factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;push-factors&quot;&gt;Push factors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1) Ecosystem&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First and foremost, I think to put it mildly: Belgium’s startup ecosystem is quite modest. There is a quite noticeable lack of succesful startup stories. If success breeds success, then the opposite rule seems to be working in Belgium, with many of the most entrepreneurial leaving. The one exception that should be noted is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imec-int.com/en&quot;&gt;Imec&lt;/a&gt;, an R&amp;amp;D hub for nano- and digital technologies. This organization has succesfully spun-off multiple very startups in its specialist field. However its area of specialization is somewhat boring to me, most of their startups are lead by people with more degrees than I can count and I’ve never been about the academic life anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2) Government&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Belgian politics are broken at a fundamental level (and unlikely to be fixed anytime soon). I won’t go into the reasons why, as this is beyond the scope of this post. This brokeness has several not so fun consequences, one of them being: high taxes for a terrible service. Take a look at this graph&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/moving-to-estonia/taxes.png&quot; alt=&quot;taxes&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Could this be the reason why people don’t start companies in Belgium?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see Belgium has the highest tax rate, now mind you I’m not &lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt; taxes. At this tax rate however I do expect to get something back: an (extremely) well-functioning political organization. A couple of months ago I posted the following on my LinkedIn:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/moving-to-estonia/linkedin.png&quot; alt=&quot;linkedin&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Translation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The link below gives a template for every kind of contract you could need as a start-up in Estonia. How come I can’t find something similar for Belgium?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tagged every one of our ministers (remember: &lt;strong&gt;6&lt;/strong&gt; governments&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;) that could have something to do with this simple questions. 1600 people saw the post, no one cared to answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With taxes this high, and a government that clearly doesn’t care about improving, I was starting to have my doubts. That’s when the Belgian police came to the resque. You see, I wasn’t 100% sure of leaving just &lt;em&gt;yet&lt;/em&gt;, I needed that last push.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to pick up some stuff from the office. Trying to be smart, I thought it’d be best if I went during noon, right in between the worst of the morning and evening traffic (Brussels is notorious for this). Unfortunately that day the police decided to have a strike and closed off the ring of Brussels. This led to the disastrous effect of everyone losing a couple of hours standing in traffic jams. This is when I mentally checked out; this country is clearly not heading in the right direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;where-to-go&quot;&gt;Where to go?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had accepted I wasn’t going to stay, at the time I still didn’t know where I would go though. I wanted it to be a city that would have a thriving startup scene, however most of the “obvious” ones are prohibitively expensive: London, Amsterdam, Stockholm, Paris. There is one however that has the reputation for being somewhat &lt;em&gt;cheap&lt;/em&gt; (although apparently that’s also changing): Berlin. I’m going to be honest: I liked the idea. However as I started to look deeper into it, it didn’t feel like that much of an improvement on the political front. You see Germany is notorious for its bureaucracy (read &lt;a href=&quot;https://peerrich.com/posts/how-i-would-start-my-next-startup-in-germany-without-a-gmbh&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;) and as someone that wants to eventually start something myself, I wasn’t looking forward to trying to explain myself in German to register my company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That left Tallinn. Tallinn is the capital of Estonia, a country that I already had on my radar for some time (with &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/balajis&quot;&gt;@balaji&lt;/a&gt; mainly responsible for this). At first I wasn’t &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; exited, it seemed cold and remote and somewhat boring? That is until I started looking into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pull-factors&quot;&gt;Pull factors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1) Government&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with the government, as that was my biggest gripe with Belgium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the first websites you’ll find if you google “estonia startup” is &lt;a href=&quot;https://startupestonia.ee/&quot;&gt;startupestonia.ee&lt;/a&gt;, I invite you to visit and have a look around. I dare you to find a governmental website that looks as good and offers as much information as that one. This was the first sign that Estonia is somewhat &lt;em&gt;different&lt;/em&gt;, someone in the political system obviously cared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That website is just scratching the surface of something larger: the Estonian government puts a lot of effort into being forward-thinking and innovative. A good example is their &lt;a href=&quot;https://e-estonia.com/solutions/e-identity/e-residency/&quot;&gt;e-Residency&lt;/a&gt; program, which allows anyone across the globe to sign up to become a digital resident of Estonia. This gives them access to all the services a regular Estonian citizen, for example: setting up an EU company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6vJTutuWPv8&quot;&gt;This&lt;/a&gt; video shows a panel of people that work for the Estonian government (one of them is an engineer!) discussing what they have done and what they wish to improve in the future. If like me you’re used to seeing politicians exclusively engage in mudslinging competitions, then this type of conversations are a like a breath of fresh air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2) Ecosystem&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If moving is the new voting, I’m voting for Estonia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tax_rates_in_Europe#/media/File:Payroll_and_income_tax_by_country.png &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_governments_in_Belgium &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
